Inventory of the Jerdone Family Papers 1753-1890, 1771-1845
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence, 1753-1890. (Box 1-10)
  - Letters, 1780-1789., 104 items. (Box 1-2)
    - Letters, 1787., 14 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
      - William DuVal, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 26 September 1787., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Reports appointment of John Howie, Wm. Hays, Mr. Holt, John McKeene and Wright Southall as referees; reports Colo[nel] Morris has stated the accounts clearly, and DuVal gives a list of categories included; also reports amount of debt due Mrs. Jerdone; sends proceedings of Federal Convention and states "if adopted will make the states more virtuous and happy than they otherwise would be."
      - Tho[mas] Mitchell, n.p. to [Francis Jerdone], n.p., 23 October 1787., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Has sent for two barrels of turpentine; has sent for Mrs. Jerdone's fabric.
      - Alex[ande]r Macaulay, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 3 November 1787., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Letter brought by Colo. Morris who has helped pull the forge out of trouble; claims Mr. Holt has been changing accounts to appearance of profit; Holt was getting business into debt; wants to make Morris a candidate for Convention and asks Jerdone's help.
      - Tho[mas] Mitchell, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 10 November 1787., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Expresses concern over Mrs. Midleton's actions to recover her fortune; refers to Polly's ingratitude to Mrs. Jerdone; reports arrival of goods and expects to send them soon; other family news.
    - Letters, 1788., 16 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 16 January 1788., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Will send the hogs out tomorrow morning; new partner, Mr. Samuel Beall of Williamsburg, has been taken on; Beall would like to meet with Jerdone; still missing money which hopes Holt will acknowledge.
      - Tho[mas] Mitchell, n.p., to [Francis Jerdone], n.p., 2 February 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Came to deliver £25 interest on £500 which he had borrowed from Jerdone; is "backward" in plantation duties so sent Isabella to deliver money; hopes to see Jerdone the following week.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 8 February 1788., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports ill health of Mrs. DuVal and how this is affecting his work; believes Circuit Courts will be a great benefit to the country; hopes to obtain £2,000 for Jerdone in court; refers to several execution of estates; expresses opinion that Constitution should be approved by states; lists states that have already approved it.
      - A. Donald, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 8 March 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports expecting ship in York River in April and requests assistance in loading her; inquires of having whole tobacco crop; reminds him that he must order goods for next fall.
      - Donald and Burton, London, [England] to Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 10 March 1788., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Explains details of carriage horses matter and why the company was sued; claims that Jerdone must pay them for the horses and al l extra expenses; gives accounts of tobacco sold and debts.
      - William DuVal, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 11 April 1788. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports decision of referees appointed by General Court in lawsuit of Mrs. Jerdone against Mr. Holt; gives sum awarded; reports loan certificates still under consideration.
      - Geo[rge] Braikenridge, York, [Virginia] to Fra[nci]s Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 29 June 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Discusses finances among Mr. Burnley, Mr. Macaulay and the Jerdones; found hoes have been sent to Jerdone.
      - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, York [County, Virginia] to her mother Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, n.p., 29 June 1788., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports arrived safely; refers to kindness of sister; refers to difficulty in leaving Mother and duty she feels toward her.
      - A. Donald, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 2 July 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Has enclosed Jerdone's account; hopes he does not complain because sales of his tobacco were not good; tobacco was not of good quality and was severely damaged; hopes he will pay his balance when convenient.
      - William DuVal, "Mont Comfort" to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 16 August 1788., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Refers to Judgment of case against Mr. Holt and its impacts; refers to Mr. Holt's reactions; advises him to wait to file other complaints until this whole account is settled.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, "Mont Comfort" to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 3 September 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Approves of deferring settlement until Mr. Johnson returns; reports sent statement to remove any injurious impressions of Mr. Holt's actions on the Chancellors' minds; reports other developments in the case; Holt has asked Marshall to represent him; Colo. Taylor's fee.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, "Mont Comfort" to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 5 September 1788., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Discusses decision to defer settlement; reports Mr. Holt's attempts to employ Mr. Marshall; explains Mr. Marshall's refusal of engagement.
      - Alex[ande]r Macauley, York [County, Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 September 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Refers to business with Mr. Holt; claims he should remain in Richmond until "Doomsday or the day after;" other family news.
      - William Browne, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 5 December 1788., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Wants to know if Jerdone wants any pork or hogs; cash is scarce and would like to sell them; corn crop doing very poorly, the season being too wet and windy; wheat doing well, yielding 700 bushels and has grown two h[ogs] h[ea]ds of tobacco; sorry to learn Mr. Douglass will remain in Scotland until spring; has been sickness this fall and lost two slaves.
      - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to her mother Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 10 December 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports correspondence from Virginia; expresses difficulty of being parted from her mother; refers to trip to England; other family news.
      - George Gairdner [?], Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 13 December 1788., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Informs Jerdone that cash [?] promised by Macaulay has not appeared; has sent two sacks of salt as leather could not be exchanged; this to be settled at maturity.
    - Letters, 1789., 18 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - W[illia]m Browne, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 3 January 1789., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to business of hogs; reports shoeing of horses; refers to failure to pass tobacco inspection legislation in the Senate.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, "Mont Comfort," [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 9 January 1789., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports judgments against Mr. Woods and Mssrs. Dickinson and Mr. Kembrough and states amounts; advises to have Colo[nel] Morris settle Holt's account.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 10 January 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to attempt to obtain payments from Dr. Currier and Mr. Gravis; refers to illness in his family and death of a son; refers to Mr. Woods' crop of tobacco; hopes late alteration in Superior Courts will result in more speedy justice.
      - T. Pope, "Mont Comfort," [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 21 February 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to letter from W[illia]m Holt; reports Mr. DuVal will advise on proper answer.
        Includes copy of letter from W[illia]m Holt, W[illia]msburg, [Virginia] to William DuVal, "Mount Comfort," February 18, [1789]. 1 page. Asking what steps Mr. Jerdone intends to take against him; also asks if business will be brought to referees or to the Chancellor.
      - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to her mother Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 11 March 1789., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to difficulty in being parted from mother; reports on her son John and his development; refers to his being "backward with his tongue"; describes her horse and some living conditions; reports receipt of mother's presents and describes difficulty with customs officials; other family news.
      - Geo[rge] Weare Bralkenridge, Ashton, [Under-Lyne, England] to his uncle Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 2 June 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Informs that all are well; is studying Ovid's Metamorphoses, Justin and Ovid's Epistles and French.
      - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to her mother, Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 10 June 1789., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Expresses sorrow in being parted from mother; gives account of when people leave the house on a normal day; refers to development of son John; refers to health; refers to rejoicing of King's recovery and great illumin[ation]; other family news.
      - A. Donald, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 14 June 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Expected Jerdone to pay debts owed to Donald and Burton of London when he was in Richmond; since not done, requests that Jerdone pay as soon as convenient.
      - A. Donald, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 9 July 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to expense of obtaining horses; refers to balance due to D[onald] and B[urton] and also amount owed in the country.
      - Thomas Mitchell, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 9 July 1789., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports receipt of desk and expresses thanks; reports on weather and its effect on crops, fears he will "loose his character as an overseer."
      - William DuVal, n.p. to [Francis Jerdone, n.p.], 29 July 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports on status of accounts and progress in receiving payment; refers to "ejectment" of Mrs. Jerdone scheduled in Williamsburg following September.
      - William DuVal, "Mont Comfort," [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 18 August 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Requests Jerdone act as witness in a suit by Mr. Pottie in Winchester; reports judgment will be against Holt in September; needs deeds of Forge at trial to prove Holt mortgaged it to Mrs. Jerdone.
      - William DuVal, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 25 August 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Asks to forward Dandridge's bonds; expects to obtain Judgment for Mr. Jerdone the following month.
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 27 August 1789., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Had Wheelwright look at carriage wheels and will have them replaced; sent two shovels and two ditching spades which he had ordered; feels Jerdone should meet with Mr. Beale as he is worthy of attention; feels important to increase number of slaves as are draining swamps.
      - William DuVal, "Mont Comfort," [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 19 October 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Refers to lack of payment by [Mr.] Daniel on his bond, outlines way to try and get payment.
      - William DuVal, "Mont Comfort," [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 4 November 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports will send Chancery's decision on case against John Winston's executors; reports on progress of case against Mr. Holt in Court of Appeals; requests delivery of papers to Mr. Charles Thomson.
      - Abram Fontaine, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 19 December 1789., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Reports statement of debt against Lewis' executors, also execution against Winston's executors and execution against Mr. Ferrell.
    - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, [Bristol, England] to her mother, Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, n.d., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Inquires of the various ailments her mother has suffered; laments how often mother is alone; refers to and inquires of her sisters; refers to outbreak of measles; inoculation of her children; refers to schools which her children will attend and their distance from house; refers to French declaration of war on England, expresses fear of war; expresses aloneness and Feeling of not belonging; refers to events taking place in France and the death of French King; other family news.
  - Letters, 1790-1799., 147 items. (Box 2-3)
    - Letters, 1790., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 2 January 1790., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Sending 40 hogs to Jerdone; suggests he send a carriage to "receive them in good order"; would like sent to him a bottle of little sweet scented [type of tobacco] seed; P.S. - has sold crop of corn and the wheat they had.
      - Sam Kello, Southhampton [County, Virginia] to [Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia], 5 January 1790., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Requests business transactions between [Jerdone's] father and Mr. Belsches for payments and accounts during years of 1772-1774; also requests copy of transactions between himself and Mr. Pottie.
      - Geo[rge] Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 1 March 1790., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Discusses quality tobacco shipped, condition of it and market; explains goods he has sent.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, "Mont Comfort," [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 9 March 1790., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Refers to business with Holt and Dudley Richardson; intends to order ex[ecutio]n against Kinsbrough [?] and someone to attend sale; explains other bonds.
      - Thomas Mitchell, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 2 May 1790., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Speaks of their speculation endeavors in the tobacco market; advises him to have nothing to do with the men involved in Major Ragland's account; thinks it would be better to deal with Burton.
      - Geo. Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 17 July 1790., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Explains goods sent and expectations for next crop of tobacco; expresses uncertainty of affairs with Spain; expresses hope war will be averted; discusses weather and crops; other family news.
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 31 July 1790., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Intends to send carriage wheels; saw William Mitchell while he was in Richmond and compliments Jerdone on his handling of a runaway blacksmith; was informed that Hugh Nelson has a blacksmith for sale; discusses corn crops; discusses Jerdone's accounts.
      - [?] Thompson, Fluvanna County, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Lo[uisa County, Virginia], 11 August 1790., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Claims is due money for the clearing of the Rivanna River; asks that Jerdone pay £8.15 to Mr. Walter who delivered letter.
    - Letters, 1791., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 January 1791., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Has sent 36 hogs but is displeased with their size and fatness; also has sent two chisels that the blacksmith has made; concerned over health of Jerdone's family but glad Mother is better; congratulates on the judgment for him against Holt. (Letter has some accounts written on back.)
      - Geo. Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 17 January 1791., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Explains goods sent; refers to "preservation from the destruction" of Jerdone family; advises Jerdone sleep with firearms nearby for safety [from slaves]; describes the "Blunderbuss" gun; gives account of weather and crops; refers to reconciliation between Spain and England; sends portrait of Sarah [Jerdone] Brackenridge; other family news.
      - William DuVal, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 2 February 1791., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Mother's mortgage is recorded and with equal validity to the original; the original has been lost, probably during the War when papers of General Court were moved; necessary to make an affidavit [?] because of replacement of original mortgage.
      - W[illia]m DuVal, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 25 March 1791., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Observes death of Wm. Holt and explains impact upon suit of Jerdone's against him; refers to business with others who have debts owed to Jerdone.
      - Geo[rge] Gair[dner], Rich[mon]d, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 22 April 1791., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Congratulates Jerdone and his mother for their successes in court; Richmond has had a visit from the President of the U.S.; describes toast of occasion; refers to crops.
      - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, "Ashton," [Bristol], [England?] to her mother, Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 30 April 1791., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Expresses concern for mother's health and her living alone; inquires of her sisters; describes her health and children's development; refers to difficulty in adjusting to England; other family news.
      - S[arah Macon] J[erdone] and F[rancis] J[erdone], Louisa [County, Virginia] to William Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia], 6 May 1791., 1 page. LS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Orders that nothing more be paid to Mr. Beale or anyone else associated with the late Mr. Holt.
      - George Weare Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to his grandmother, Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, [2]0 July 1791., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Reports on his mother's [Sarah Jerdone Braikenridge] health; reports on brothers and sisters development; comments on "Ashton"; refers to affairs in France; other family news.
      - Geo. Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 1 August 1791., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Apologizes for damage done to goods; explains current shipment of goods; reports British strong economy and rise in prices for woolens and iron products; refers to British battleships prepared for emergency and affairs in France.
      - Sarah [Jerdone] Braikenridge, "Ashton," [England] to her mother, Sarah [Macon] Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 3 August 1791., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses Mother's health and family; reports development of family; describes rickets; visit to cotton mill; reports weather and effect on crops; refers to lawsuits of Jerdone's; refers to events taking place in France; other Family news.
    - Letters, 1792., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 5 January 1792., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Has sent overseer 25 hogs; has sent Jerdone bushels of holly berries and Church's oats [?] to be sowed; waited for Jerdone to finds a market for their corn but finally made an agreement with [Alexander] Macaulay; Mr. Macaulay is working toward agreement on the disputed accounts of Mr. Holt.
      - Geo. Weare Braikenridge, "Ashton," n[ea]r Bristol, [England] to his uncle, [Francis] Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 20 February 1792., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Reports Mother's health is improved; speaks of brothers and himself; reports on weather; lists flowers in bloom; other family news.
      - Geo. Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 22 February 1792., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Reports goods sent; refers to price increases and blames this on peace in Europe.
      - Coulter Robertson and Company, Barbados to Alex McCall, Antigua, 18 March 1792., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Describes order made by Mr. Thompson Rowland through Mssrs. Sutherland and McKee for the Coulter Robertson Co.
      - George Weare Braikenridge, Ashton [under-Lyne], Bristol, [England] to his uncle, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County], Virginia, 13 August 1792., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Sorry to hear the family was ill, the captain who delivered his letters is retiring to New York; there have been debates in Parliament over the abolition of slave trade; describes incidents occurring in the West Indies; has been a boycott of sugar; feels this is silly; other family news.
      - Geo. Gairdner, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 17 August 1792., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Refers to sending rum; explains how to enhance its flavor; refers to crops; other family news.
      - Geo. Braikenridge, Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 18 August 1792., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Refers to goods ordered; needs more notice as does not order from dealer if he can get from manufacturer; explains increased prices on wine; other news concerning shipping.
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 12 September 1792., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Cancels plans made to travel northward; his daughter Polly died August 19, 1792.
    - Letters, 1793., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 3 January 1793., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Reports hog business; refers to lawsuits; refers to crops; requests meeting in Richmond or Hanovertown; other family news.
      - W[illia]m Douglass, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 14 February 1793., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Two hogs are missing; has enclosed description and accounts of P[rovidence] Forge estate; has sold surplus of wheat to Mssrs. Freeland and Gillies for five shillings sterling per bushel; is working on terms for corn crop now at 18 shillings sterling per bar[re]l; has not heard from friends in Jedburgh, [Scotland] and becoming uneasy.
      - Geo[rge] Gairdner, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 1 March 1793., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Has sent a newspaper describing incidents in Europe; relates his opinions in regard to American liberty and influence on Europe; other family news.
      - Geo[rge] Gairdner, Richmond, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 23 March 1793., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Sends regards of "Mr. M."; Mr. M. has sent, a "hamper porter" [port wine]; will leave the eulogium on the port's quality to Jerdone.